<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article class="specification" lang="en" status="draft">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Mindquarry Collaboration Server Feature Documentation</title>

    <subtitle>Description of the features provided by the Mindquarry Team
    Suite</subtitle>

    <abstract>
      <para>This document describes the features of the Mindquarry Team Suite
      as well as their purpose and usage.</para>
    </abstract>

    <author>
      <firstname>Alexander</firstname>

      <surname>Klimetschek</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle>Chief Architect</jobtitle>

        <orgname>Mindquarry GmbH</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <author>
      <firstname>Alexander</firstname>

      <surname>Saar</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle>Chief Technology Officer</jobtitle>

        <orgname>Mindquarry GmbH</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <address>August-Bebel-Str. 88, D-14482 Potsdam</address>

    <date>07. Dezember 2006</date>

    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year>

      <holder>Mindquarry GmbH</holder>
    </copyright>

    <releaseinfo>Version 1.0</releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Feature Description</title>

    <para>The following sections describes the features provided by the
    Mindquarry Open Source Collaboration Server in Version 1.0. The web
    application and web interface is seperated into several components
    (teamspace, workspace, wiki and tasks); a desktop client connects the
    desktop computer with the server for things best done on the computer
    (like files of the workspaces); the client uses a public HTTP Rest
    API.</para>

    <section>
      <title>General</title>

      <para>The overall system has the following basics:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Users</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Users have different views on the system, ie. depending in
            which teams they are. Each user account represents a single human
            being, identified by a unique user id, name and by a photo
            wherever possible in the user interface. The user profile also
            contains an email address and a description of the user's skills.
            There is a special user with id "admin" for administrative
            work.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Teams</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Teams represent the basic structure for all data in the
            Mindquarry system. They depict people working together on
            something (you can call it projects). Each team has its own
            workspace, wiki and task area. A team has a unique id, a name and
            a short description.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Web interface commons</title>

      <para>The following common features are provided by the Mindquarry
      Collaboration Server web interface:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="C1000">
          <term>Login/Logout</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Users login and logout with their user id and a password.
            All authentication is done via HTTP Basic Auth, which allows
            REST-style clients like the Desktop client to use the same
            authentication mechanism. The web user interface provides a
            familar form-based login which hides HTTP authentication. If a
            direct link is clicked when the user is not logged in (e.g. sent
            via email), the login form will redirect to the link on successful
            login. The name of the logged-in user will be displayed in the
            top-right of each page with a log out link next to it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="C2000">
          <term>Authorization</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>In the first version authorization is very simple and
            non-configurable: users have full read and write access to the
            teamspaces they belong to, but cannot create teams or other users.
            Creating teams and users is only possible with the admin
            account.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="C3000">
          <term>Quick Search</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A search box is visible on all pages in the top-left which
            allows to enter simple search words and quickly returns the result
            in a small popup window. In Version 1.0 only wiki pages and tasks
            areas are searched, the results are grouped accordingly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Teams</title>

      <para>The Teamspace Component is the adminstrative area where the teams
      and users that collaborate are managed for the system:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="T1000">
          <term>Create User</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The "admin" user can create a user from the teamspace
            overview page. All basic data (id, password, photo, first name,
            surname, email and skill description) can be entered in a
            dialog.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="T2000">
          <term>Change User Settings</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Each user can change his own profile via a click on his user
            id displayed in the top left. The user id cannot be
            changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="T3000">
          <term>Create Team</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The "admin" user can create a new team from the teamspace
            overview page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="T4000">
          <term>Add/Remove Team Members</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users of a team and the "admin" user can add and remove
            members to their team. Adding a user to a team is only possible by
            the "admin" user in the first place.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="T5000">
          <term>Change Team Settings</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users of a team can change the name and the description
            of the team at any time. The team id cannot be changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tasks</title>

      <para>The Tasks Component allows to manage any kind of work tasks and
      their relations:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Task</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A task is described by a number of fields, where only two
            are required (title and status). The other fields can be added on
            demand.</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Title</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(required) The short description of the task, visible
                  as link on other pages (task lists, search results,
                  etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Status</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(required) Either new, running, paused or done to
                  indicate the current general status of the task.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Summary</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A text with additional information
                  complementing the title. Displayed on the task list
                  page.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Date</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A date connected with the task. Could be
                  the deadline, for example.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Description</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A long, rich-text formatted description of
                  the task.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>People</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A list of people/users connected to this
                  task. Each person has a role, which can be freely defined.
                  E.g. "someuser" with role "responsible". People can be
                  choosen from the list of users of the current team.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Archived</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A checkbox to indicate that this task is no
                  longer under active use and should be in the archive (not
                  yet in place).</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Dependencies</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>(optional) A list of dependencies to other tasks of
                  this team. As with people, the role can be freely defined.
                  Typcial dependencies are "depends on", "duplicate of",
                  "before" etc.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I1000">
          <term>Create Task</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users of a team can create a task. The task initially
            has the two required fields, title and status. The unique id for a
            task is an automatically calculated consecutive number.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I2000">
          <term>Change Task</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>All users of a team can modify a task. A task cannot be
            deleted, only archived. Editing is possible by clicking on one
            field to edit this field only or by clicking on "Edit all" to edit
            all fields and to change which fields should be present.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I3000">
          <term>List Tasks</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A list of tasks for a teamspace.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I4000">
          <term>Create Task Filter</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A filter is an intelligent list of tasks (report) which
            filters only specific tasks according to rules. A rule might be
            "Field status is running" to give all currently running tasks.
            Filters belong to a teamspace and filter the tasks of that
            teamspace. Filters can be saved under a descriptive name.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I5000">
          <term>View/Change Task Filter</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A filter can be viewed in which the filtered list of tasks
            is recalculated. The rules can be changed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="I6000">
          <term>List Filters</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The list of filters for the task area of a teamspace are
            displayed on the overview and the task list page.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Wiki</title>

      <para>The Wiki Component provides a wiki for each team to store ideas,
      notes, any kind of fluent knowledge:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Wiki page</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A wiki page consists of a title and a content, which is a
            rich-text field. Editing is fully WYSIWYG, there is no special
            wiki syntax.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="W1000">
          <term>Create Wiki Page</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A wiki page can be created via a click on the "create page"
            button or by typing a not-yet-existing name of the page in the
            URL. In the first case the unique name of a wiki page is
            automatically derived from the title.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="W2000">
          <term>Change Wiki Page</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The title and the content can be changed at any time. The
            unique name cannot be changed. Editing is possible by clicking on
            the title or content to edit those specifically or by clicking on
            "Edit all" to edit both.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="W3000">
          <term>Link Wiki Pages</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>It is possible to add hyperlinks to other wiki pages in the
            same wiki in the content field. There are two buttons, that can be
            used after marking a piece of text that should become the link.
            One creates a link to the page name based on the selected text,
            the other presents a dialog where a list of the wiki pages is
            shown or an external URL (starting with http:// or https://) can
            be entered.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="W4000">
          <term>Start Page</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A fixed "Start" page is automatically created and can be
            reached via the wiki overview page. It should be used as the entry
            point for the wiki.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Workspace Management</title>

      <para>The Workspace Component allows to view the files and the structure
      of the working files shared by each each time online:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="F1000">
          <term>Browse Workspace Directories</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The directory structure of the versioned workspace can be
            browsed. The latest version number, timestamp, change comment,
            name and photo of the user who made the change will be
            displayed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="F2000">
          <term>Browse Workspace Versions</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Old versions can be browsed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="F3000">
          <term>View Workspace Files</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Workspace files can be downloaded, either displayed in the
            browser if they are text files or saved on the local computer if
            they are binary files.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="F4000">
          <term>RSS/Atom Feed For Changes</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A link to an RSS feed provides notification of changed files
            for RSS readers.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Desktop Client</title>

      <para>The Mindquarry Desktop Client runs on the computer of a user and
      improves the work by connecting to the server:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Small Tray Icon</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The client is an unobtrusive but always running application
            that will reside in the "tray" of the operating system (this
            depends on the actual OS). Clicking on the tray icon will show a
            small window with all important information.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="D1000">
          <term>Synchronize Workspaces</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatically synchronizes the workspaces for the teams the
            user belongs to into a directory on the local hard drive. Any
            changes done by the team members will be "downloaded" into the
            local directory (after a notification) and any changes done by the
            user can be shared with the rest of the team on demand.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="D2000">
          <term>List Tasks</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A list of a user's task is displayed in the small
            window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="D3000">
          <term>Finish Tasks</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>A task can be stopped from within the window.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HTTP REST Client API</title>

      <para>There is a REST-style interface for computer-based clients to
      exchange information with the Mindquarry Collaboration Server. All data
      is in XML formats which incorporate usage of hyperlinks. Authentication
      must be done with a valid user account via HTTP basic authentication for
      each request:</para>

      <section>
        <title>Tasks</title>

        <para><variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Get List of Tasks</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The list of tasks for a teamspace can be retrieved via a
                HTTP GET on the URL
                <code>/tasks/&lt;team-id&gt;/</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Read a Task</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A task including all data can be retrieved via a HTTP
                GET on the URL
                <code>/tasks/&lt;team-id&gt;/&lt;task-id&gt;.xml</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Create a Task</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A new task can be created by sending a task in the
                correct XML format with an HTTP PUT on the URL
                <code>/tasks/&lt;team-id&gt;/new</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Change a Task</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A task can be changed/overwritten with an HTTP PUT
                including the new XML data on the URL
                <code>/tasks/&lt;team-id&gt;/&lt;task-id&gt;.xml</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Wiki</title>

        <para><variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Get List of Wiki pages</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>The list of wiki pages for a teamspace can be retrieved
                via a HTTP GET on the URL
                <code>/wiki/&lt;team-id&gt;/</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Read a Wiki page</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A wiki page XML data can be retrieved via a HTTP GET on
                the URL
                <code>/wiki/&lt;team-id&gt;/&lt;pagename&gt;</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Create a Wiki page</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A new wiki page can be created by sending a page in the
                correct XML format with an HTTP PUT on the URL
                <code>/wiki/&lt;team-id&gt;/new</code> or by writing to a
                non-existing page name
                <code>/wiki/&lt;team-id&gt;/&lt;new-pagename&gt;</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
              <term>Change a Wiki page</term>

              <listitem>
                <para>A wiki page can be changed/overwritten with an HTTP PUT
                including the new XML data on the URL
                <code>/wiki/&lt;team-id&gt;/&lt;pagename&gt;</code></para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist></para>
        </section>

    </section>
  </section>
</article>