<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- commenting out the dtd reference for fun and performance (until catalogs
are working or we are using docbook 5 -->
<!--DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"-->
<book>
  <title>Mindquarry User Guide</title>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para id="mindquarry.introduction">Mindquarry is a web-application that
    supports your teamwork by combining file sharing, Wiki for knowledge
    management and collaborative task management. </para>

    <para>This user guide will introduce the most important features of the
    Mindquarry system.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Managing Teams with Mindquarry</title>

    <para id="teams.introduction">With Mindquarry teams you can see your teams
    and team members. Team managers can invite members. </para>

    <para>You can see all your teams in a list. This list contains the team's
    name, description and photos of some of the team members. You can use the
    slider allows to the left and the right of the team member's photos to
    scroll through the list of team members.</para>

    <para>If you would like to see more details of the team or change team
    settings or invite team members (only for team managers), click the team's
    name. Now you see all details for the team including all team
    members.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Adding and Removing Team Members</title>

      <para>To add or remove team members click the <guibutton>Team
      members</guibutton> button in the details view of your team. In the
      resulting dialog you will see your team memers on the left (scroll to
      see all) and other people registred in the Mindquarry Collaboration
      Server on the right.</para>

      <para>If you would like to add a team member, just click its profile on
      the right side, if you would like to remove a team member, click its
      profile on the left side. When you are finished, click done.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editing a Team's Details</title>

      <para>You can edit a team's details like name and description by
      clicking the <guibutton>Edit settings</guibutton> button in the details
      view of your team and editing the settings in the dialog
      appearing.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Managing Files with Mindquarry</title>

    <para id="files.introduction">Mindquarry file sharing stores all your
    documents and keeps a history of changes.</para>

    <para>With Mindquarry file sharing you can synchronize shared files with
    your desktop, view shared files in the Mindquarry web application and see
    the history of changes made to your team's files.</para>

    <section id="files.desktop.synchronization">
      <title>Synchronizing with Your Desktop</title>

      <para>There are various ways to access the files shared with your team
      using the Mindquarry Collaboration Server. This section explain the most
      common ways to access these files.</para>

      <tip id="getting.mindquarry.files">
        <title>How to access shared files</title>

        <para>The files shown in the file sharing browser are shared by all
        team members. In order to edit them and to share your changes, you
        need to synchronize the shared folder with your desktop. There are
        three ways to do this:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Using the <link
            linkend="file.desktop.client"><productname>Mindquarry Desktop
            Client</productname></link>. The <productname>Mindquarry Desktop
            Client</productname> requires <productname>Microsoft
            Windows</productname> and <productname>Java</productname>
            <productnumber>5</productnumber> and synchronizes all your
            teamspaces with the <productname>Mindquarry Collaboration
            Server</productname> automatically. To install the
            <productname>Mindquarry Desktop Client</productname>, click the
            <guilabel>Client</guilabel> link in the footer of this
            page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using the <link
            linkend="file.subversion.client">Subversion</link> program.
            Mindquarry is fully <ulink
            url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</ulink> compatible,
            meaning you can use any Subversion client like <ulink
            url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org">TortoiseSVN</ulink>, <ulink
            url="http://www.syntevo.com/smartsvn/">SmartSVN</ulink> or <ulink
            url="http://rapidsvn.tigris.org/">RapidSVN</ulink> to synchronize
            your files.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using <link
            linkend="mindquarry.webdav.support">WebDAV</link>. You can use the
            builtin-WebDAV-support of your operating system to access the
            shared files and read and write them on the fly.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </tip>

      <section id="file.desktop.client">
        <title>Mindquarry Desktop Client</title>

        <para>The Mindquarry Desktop Client is installed via Java Webstart.
        When clicking the <guibutton>Synchronize now</guibutton> button in the
        workspace browser or the <guilabel>client</guilabel> link in the
        footer of the Mindquarry Web Application, your browser will download a
        small file that will install the Mindquarry Desktop Client on your
        computer and start it automatically. The general procedure is:</para>

        <procedure>
          <step>
            <para>Click the Client link</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Java WebStart will start downloading your personalized
            Mindquarry Desktop Client and ask you for your username and
            password to access your personalized Mindquarry Desktop
            Client.</para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>Once the client is downloaded, Java WebStart will launch the
            Client automatically. </para>
          </step>

          <step>
            <para>In order to connect to your Mindquarry Collaboration Server,
            you need to enter your username and password to the Mindquarry
            Desktop client.</para>
          </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>The Mindquarry Desktop client features a
        <guibutton>Synchronize</guibutton> button. Clicking this button the
        first time will download all shared files from the Mindquarry
        Collaboration Server that you can access to your desktop computer.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>Depending on the size and number of shared files, this could
          take some time. </para>
        </note>

        <para>Whenever you click this synchronize button again, the Mindquarry
        Desktop Client will download all changed files from the Mindquarry
        Collaboration Server to your desktop computer and will upload all
        files modified or added on your desktop computer to the Mindquarry
        Collaboration Server, so they become accessible by other team
        members.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="file.subversion.client">
        <title>Subversion Support</title>

        <para>Mindquarry's file sharing is 100% compatible to the open source
        version control system Subversion. You can use any Subversion client
        to synchronize your files. The relevant repository
        <abbrev>URL</abbrev> is <literal><replaceable
        role="replaceable">http://your.mindquarryserver.com/repos</replaceable>/teamname/trunk/</literal>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="mindquarry.webdav.support">
        <title>WebDAV Support</title>

        <para>Mindquarry's file sharing is 100% compatible to the WebDAV file
        sharing protocol. You can use your operating systems capability to
        mount WebDAV folders to access the shared document at real-time. The
        relevant repository <abbrev>URL</abbrev> is <literal><replaceable
        role="replaceable">http://your.mindquarryserver.com/repos</replaceable>/teamname/trunk/</literal>.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Browsing Shared Files</title>

      <para>The Mindquarry file sharing block includes a listing of all your
      teams. For each team you have the ability to browse files or view
      changed files<footnote>
          <para>Convered in <xref linkend="files.change.history" /></para>
        </footnote>.</para>

      <para>The file browser shows you the files in the base directory of your
      team's shared files, shows subdirectories and files. For each file there
      is information about file size, date of last modification, the author of
      the last modification and the comment the last author made when
      synchronizing her files.</para>

      <para>You can expand subdirectories by clicking on the small
      <guiicon>plus-icon</guiicon> or browse into the subdirectory by clicking
      the directory name. When browsing a subdirectory, you will see a arrow
      pointing up allowing you to switch back to the parent directory.</para>

      <para>An additional feature is the ability to see previous states of the
      shared files by clicking the left and right arrows on to to go back to
      an earlier (left) or later (right) stage.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="files.change.history">
      <title>History of Changes</title>

      <para>The history of changes allows you to keep track with your
      colleagues work. You will see what colleague changed what files at what
      point of time. As an additional feature, you can subscribe to the feed
      of changes using an feed reader<footnote>
          <para>A feed reader will notify you when changes have been made to a
          file sharing directory you subscribed to. It allows you to stay
          informed without having to visit the history of changes page
          regularily.</para>
        </footnote>.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Sharing Ideas with Mindquarry</title>

    <para id="wiki.introduction">The Wiki is your personal idea-store,
    blackboard and glossary for sharing information and creativity.</para>

    <para>Each team's wiki consists of a list of Wiki pages. You can see this
    list by clicking the <guilabel>All pages</guilabel> link at the bottom of
    each Wiki page.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Editing Wiki Pages</title>

      <para>In order to edit a Wiki page's content, you have to double-click
      the Wiki page. After editing or formatting the text, click the
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button to save your changes. If you would
      like to cancel the editing and revert the page to the original content,
      click the <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button.</para>

      <para>In order to edit a Wiki page's title, double-click the title and
      click the Save button to save and share your changes. Use the
      <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button to cancel editing a title.</para>

      <para>You can edit a Wiki page's title and content at once by clicking
      the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. After clicking this button, the
      whole page becomes editable and you can use the
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button to save your changes and the
      <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button to revert the page to the original
      state.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Linking Wiki Pages</title>

      <para>In order to create links between two Wiki pages, you have to edit
      one Wiki page and turn a part of it's text content into a link. The
      general procedure is:</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Start editing the page by clicking edit or double-clicking the
          page's content.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Highlight a word or phrase in the Wiki page editor.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Click the create link button in the toolbar.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
          <para>Continue editing the page and save your changes.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>

      <para>Afterwards all the new link can be clicked and will lead you to
      the new page. If this page already exists, you will see it's contents.
      If it is a completely new page, you will be able to edit the page's
      contents right away.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>You can use the <guibutton>advanced link</guibutton> button in
        the toolbar if you would like to specify the target of the newly
        created link. </para>
      </tip>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Managing Tasks with Mindquarry</title>

    <para id="tasks.introduction">With the task management block you can see
    your todo list and assign tasks to your team members.</para>

    <para>Each team's task list consits of a list of tasks. Each tasks has a
    number of detail fields like title, status, due date or description. Some
    of these fields are required, others are optional and can be enabled
    on-demand.</para>

    <para>You can define a number of task filters for each team. Task filters
    are lists of tasks with common values, e.g. all tasks with high
    priority.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Editing Tasks</title>

      <para>After clicking the <guibutton>new task</guibutton> button in the
      task list, a new task is created. You can edit title by typing a title
      in the title field and status by pressing one of the status
      buttons.</para>

      <para>Additionally you can select optional fields from the list of
      available fields by clicking the button for the desired field. After
      clicking for instance the <guibutton>Summary</guibutton> button, a new
      field <guilabel>Summary</guilabel> will appear and you are able to edit
      its contents. Clicking the <guibutton>Summary</guibutton> button again
      will remove this fields.</para>

      <para>When you are finished editing the task, click on the
      <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button. This will save your changes and make
      them visible to other team members. Clicking the
      <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button resets the task list to the
      original state before you started editing or before you created a new
      task.</para>

      <para>When viewing a task, you can switch back to the edit mode by
      clicking the <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> button. You can also edit
      single fields by double-clicking the field's value, e.g. by
      double-clicking the title of the task, you are able to edit the
      title.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating Filters</title>

      <para>In order to reduce the list of tasks you can create a filter by
      clicking the <guibutton>New filter</guibutton> button in the team's task
      list. A filter allows you to define a number of contitions the tasks
      shown have to fulfil. You can select whether all or only some conditions
      have to be met to display a task in the list.</para>

      <para>For each condition, you select a field to filter for, enter a
      desired value and wether the field should excactly match the value or
      should just contain the value.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>